<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Retroshare on Mohammed Saud</title>
    <link>https://saud.gq/tags/retroshare/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Retroshare on Mohammed Saud</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 24 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://saud.gq/tags/retroshare/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Web Interface for Retroshare - Update 2</title>
      <link>https://saud.gq/posts/2019/07/web-interface-for-retroshare-update-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://saud.gq/posts/2019/07/web-interface-for-retroshare-update-2/</guid>
      <description>This is a mirror of a post I wrote on the Freifunk blog.
 I Realized that the visual appearance of the application felt very bland and uninteresting, so I decided to shift some of my focus to the design and visual aspect of the UI. I did plenty of reading about UI/UX design principles and modern best practices during this time. And looks like it turned out pretty well, and is definitely a good improvement from the previous appearance.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Web Interface for Retroshare - Update 1</title>
      <link>https://saud.gq/posts/2019/06/web-interface-for-retroshare-update-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://saud.gq/posts/2019/06/web-interface-for-retroshare-update-1/</guid>
      <description>This is a mirror of a post I wrote on the Freifunk blog.
 Since the first post, there has been quite a lot of progress on development of the new Web Interface for Retroshare.
As the build process is not using any JavaScript-specific tools, I spent a lot of time making sure that the development process was made as streamlined as possible. All the components are logically isolated and functionality moved to their relevant places.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A new Web Interface for Retroshare</title>
      <link>https://saud.gq/posts/2019/05/a-new-web-interface-for-retroshare/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://saud.gq/posts/2019/05/a-new-web-interface-for-retroshare/</guid>
      <description>This is a mirror of a post I wrote on the Freifunk blog.
 The Retroshare communication platform already has a preliminary web interface. But it is severely limited, supports only the basic of interactions with the client, and does not have the nice design and beautiful visual interface that the modern web platform makes possible. This GSoC project will be about creating an entirely new web interface for Retroshare using it’s JSON API to handle all communication between the WebUI and the client.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>